Guide to the Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh, John Gabbert Bowman, Administrative Files, 1921-1945 UA.2.10.1921-1945
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Correspondence: G. Stanley Rupp (Box 8, Folder 70, Folder 70a)
  Many 'thank you' letters for contributions to the University; List of gifts from J.C. Trees of October 23, 1940; Accounting for Cathedral of Learning, by Treasurer G.S. Rupp; Statement of construction costs for Tuck Shop on the Bigelow Boulevard side (red.) May 1940; Petty Memorial Room fund from First Baptist Church, October 1939; Women's Student Health Service established on 28th floor of the Cathedral of Learning, 1939; List of Scholarship fund of A.W. Mellon Educational and Charitable Trust Fund as of July 1, 1938; Cathedral of Learning construction charges and receipts of expenditures; June 1, 1936 – December 22, 1938; Mrs. Howard Irish gave a walnut desk with roll top which was the property of Mrs. Irish's grandfather, 1938; George Bevier added to the Bevier Fund, 1937; List of gifts of land buildings, equipment, payment or indebtedness, 1921-35; Letter from Auditor to Mrs. Ethelbert Nevin regarding payment in full for remaining Nevin manuscripts, January 23, 1935; January 3, 1934 letter showing that Frederic Schaefer gave the money for the manuscripts, also letters on October 5, 1933 and August 4, 1933; Development program for the Library in the Cathedral of Learning, 1935; Listing of assets of Darlington memorial Building Fund, June 30, 1934; List of gifts of David L. Gillespie as of May 10, 1934; Document sent to J. Matusenski by Rector of University of Krakow, and a stone for the Polish Nationality room, both put in the University vault for safe keeping, October 1933; Treasurer statements, 1926-40
- Correspondence: G. Stanley Rupp (Box 8, Folder 71, Folder 71a)
  Nationality Rooms Book, donation by Mr. Leon Falk for publication of the book, January 8, 1947; 15 drawings were purchased from Dr. A. Avinoff, the money donated by Miss Helen C. Frick, March 2, 1944; Galen C. Hartman gave Crucible steel Co. of American stock to establish "Galen C. Hartman Library Fund" for books, November 8, 1945; List of land purchases for Medical Center, February 14, 1945; The University reimbursed for expenses of the Civil Affairs Specialists Training Program, by the U.S. Government, May 31, 1944; The University was paid for the use of its facilities by the Army Air Forces and A.S.T.P., February 18, 1944; List of contributors to the building fund for the Cathedral of Learning, 1934; List of items purchased, March 24, 1943 for the Darlington Library; List of contributions from A.W. and R.B. Mellon; Condensed financial report of the Falk Elementary School from its opening in 1931/32 to 1941/42, also, 1941 Financial memorandum; List of buildings on Schenley Farms (Upper campus) Year completed and cost as of July 1, 1941; Treasurer's report of assets of lands, buildings, etc, as of July 1, 1941; Copy of bill from R.C.A. Manufacturing Co., for the Electron microscope, November 1941 cost of $9500; University purchased a Collection of Italian drawings from Mary Burgwin Denny (Mrs. Harmar Denny) with funds donated by George H. Clapp, in 1941; Agreement with U.S. Department of Interior through Bureau of Mines for Anesthesia Research in 1941; List of subscribers to building fund for Cathedral of Learning, May 25, 1934
- Correspondence: Scaife - Sage (Box 9, Folder 72)
  Correspondence of Alan M. Scaife and Chancellor Bowman relative to Board of Trustees, 1935-43; Sandburg, Carl statement on Cathedral of Learning; Letters: M.E. Sadler
- Correspondence: Scaife Foundation (Box 9, Folder 73)
  Copy of "Indenture of Trust creating the Sarah Mellon Scaife Foundation, December 1941;" Statements of financial condition of the Fund, 1942-1945
- Correspondence: Schenley Farms - Schenley Ballroom (Box 9, Folder 74)
  Photocopy of a picture taken in 1897 of the Schenley Farms District by Ralph W. Johnston (Photo removed for scanning in Nov. 2009 will be filed in the media room with other University images); Schenley Ballroom composed of objects from Picnic House, home of the Schenley's – given by William S. Miller, President of Steelwood Corp., 1941; Handwritten letter of Mrs. Mary E. Farquharson (granddaughter of Mrs. Schenley) on the preservation of the Ballroom by the University.
- Correspondence from and about Frederic Schaefer (Box 9, Folder 75)
  Correspondence with Chancellor Bowman concerning the Cathedral of Learning and the planning of a Scandinavian Nationality Classroom; Plans to establish a "Child Guidance Center;" Hindenburg Medal and a British medal, 1910-1935
- Correspondence: Scully - Service Flag (Box 9, Folder 77)
  Suggestion that students apprentice in Municipal government, 1940; Description of a new seal for the University, 1937; World War I service flag and Air Corps Training detachment flag for World War II (location as of 1947); Henry Sayer Scribner, Hon Doctor of Letters conferred June 29; Letters from C.E. Seashore
- Seismograph Station (Box 9, Folder 77)
  Dr. George Clapp donated a Seismograph to the university, 1929; Correspondence, reports, photograph and installation
- Sesquicentennial publicity (Box 9, Folder 78)
  Sesquicentennial Pitt News; Pamphlets: Swedish room in the Cathedral of Learning; The American Swedish monthly November 19, 1936 and December 1936; Presbyterian Banner, February 25, 1937; Bulletin Index February 25, 1937; Christian Science Monitor, and Alumni Review, February 25, 1937; see also FF 152 and 0/10/4/2.; Phonograph records (four) made of aluminum depict background and history of the University – addresses of Agnes L. Starrett, Dr. Jock Bane Sutherland, Dr. P.V. MacParlane, remarks of Mr. Norman McCloed and Chancellor Bowman's address (missing from folder no other location given (11/2009)
- Correspondence: Schockley - Slesinger (Box 9, Folder 79)
  Pamphlet: Growth of graduate study (1931) on p. 5 is list of degrees conferred 1891-1912, 1912-1931; various enrollment statistics, also; Article on Lee Pau Sieg, June 7, 193?; Clock designed and built in 1845 by Reinhold Siedle given to University, 1937; Shockley letters re; Johnstown credits; Sidhu letter, Hooker letter on Sigma Xi, Earnest Slessinger case
- Correspondence: Alexander Siverman (Box 9, Folder 80)
  Manuscript of "Research history of the Department of chemistry" by Alexander Silverman, rev. November 12, 1948; Honorary Doctor of Science conferred, June 1930; Photograph of Silverman; Information on Portland Vase replica
- Pitt Stadium (Box 10, Folder 81)
  Letters from Richard K. Mellon (Major, U.S. Army) regarding the Army War Show to be held in the stadium on June 1942; Varsity Letter Club; Minutes of Athletic Council, July 21, 1937 – policy; Letter on Code of Conduct for athletes; Taxes assessed on stadium, 1935; List of stadium bond holders, 1934; Constitution and by-laws, University of Pittsburgh Athletic Council, Rev. to April 1, 1920; Brochure for sale of stadium bonds, $2,100,000 in 1924; Some information on the development and construction of the Stadium including the report to the Board of Trustees; Memo on stadium: to be located on Bailey property
- Correspondence and articles: Agnes Lynch Starrett (Box 10, Folder 82)
  Drafts of various articles written by Starrett; Article about drawings of Nationality Rooms by Dr. Andrey Avinoff; Paper on the H.C. Frick family; Articles on some of the Nationality rooms; Short history of the university; Typed copy of the Bridges poem: "... for you the very stars are new" used in the commons room. Typed copy of a letter from William Makepeace Thackeray to Henry Marie Brackenridge, 1853; Memoirs of late Reverend Dr. Black; "Reality" essay on the death of Roy J. Ruane, killed in the war; Draft of a biography of Frick ("A Fair Green Village"); Photograph of a lecture on astronomy from the Day book of Rev. John Taylor, principal of the Pittsburgh Academy from 1801-1807
- Correspondence: Smith - Stewart (Box 10, Folder 83)
  Edward Smith estate; "Happy Scholar" by J. Duncan Spaeth – address at University, May 13, 1932; Story of the "University spoon"; Letters: Spear, Simms-St Martini (langley memorial), Hamilton Stewart, Smith, Inaugural address of Herbert Lincoln Spencer (Chatham College)
- State Appropriations (Box 10, Folder 84)
  Correspondence with John M. Walker; Brief submitted by University to Committee of the House of Representatives, May 18, 1935; Report of Legislative Committee appointed pursuant to resolution no. 61, session 1935-7; Table of "Sources of receipts" for 1924/25-1933/34; Long questionnaire concerning the University, 1934 from John Price Jones Corp.; Legislative askings, fact, 1923-25
- State Department of Public Instruction, reports and correspondence (Box 10, Folder 85)
  Reports of the University to the Department; 1931-1946/47 gives number of faculty, salaries, degrees, students and their degrees, value of grounds, number of buildings, volumes in the library, acres for campus; Accreditation for public instruction
- State Historical Commission collection of University's Activities for WWII (Box 10, Folder 86)
  State Historical Commission collection of University's Activities for WWII: sale of war bonds, reports of medical, nursing and engineering schools, Hospital Unit 27
- Stone - Student Alliance (Box 10, Folder 87)
  Contract cancelled with Stone & Webster Engineering Corp. for work on the Cathedral of Learning, March 1936; Blue print, conjectural Restoration of first Pittsburgh Academy building by Charles M. and Edward Stotz, front and side elevation 1937; Facts and maps about early Pittsburgh; Application to the Student-Faculty Association (Club charter) by Student Alliance; Swatrzel letter
- Summer Session Convocation Programs (Box 10, Folder 88)
  Convocation Programs for Summer Sessions 1923-1930, 1933; Some have notes
- Correspondence: Sutherland - Temple University (Box 10, Folder 89)
  Sutherland resignation, Sutherland Room consideration, Temple University Communication
- Tenure, Reports and Correspondence (Box 10, Folder 90)
  1916 document by Chancellor McCormick on tenure; Long and short reports of Study Committee elected by the faculties of the schools, 1936
- Correspondence: Tippetts - Thompson (Thaw) (Box 10, Folder 91)
  Correspondence of Mrs. Mary Thaw Thompson and Chancellor Bowman about her gift; The marble bust of Dr. Alexander Blair Thaw and the donation of books and mss to the Darlington Collection; Dr. Francis N. Thorpe's letter giving his technical library of Constitutional Law (about 1500 to 2000 titles to the University; Charles S. Tippetts and Chancellor Bowman's correspondence concerning his joining the staff
- Correspondence: Thompson - Traux (Box 10, Folder 92)
  Letters: A.M. Thompson, George J. Thompson, Torrance, Shotts about Town Hall site on Ruskin, C.C. Traux
- Correspondence and Reports: Board of Trustees (Box 11, Folder 93)
  Estate of Margaret Young bequeathed; Special report of Executive Committee to Board of Trustees that Chancellor Bowman desires to be relieved of Chancellorship duties; Lists of Trustees; Minutes of Committee of Planning of Bd., 1948; Resolution passed concerning Chancellor Bowman, June 12, 1945; Partia report of executive Committee on the Report of the Special Investigating Committee, December 11, 1939; Chancellor's notes on Board meetings; Letters from Armed Forces personnel, 1942; List of members of faculty in military; Letters concerning Dr. Fitzgerald when he dad an opportunity to be President of the University of Vermont; FF 93A: Notes on Board meetings, 1921-1928; Letter to Trustees about the report of its Committee of Investigation on which six months were spent – Chancellor had no knowledge of "input" – gives wrong impression of University; Oath taken by members of Board; List of trustees including place of employment; List of improvements and additions to the educational facilities; 1934-35; Comparative data on 650 and 450 foot buildings; Gifts to the university; Material on the Building Fund; Descriptions of the different parts of the Cathedral of Learning; Letters of introduction Ruth Crawford Mitchell to Presidents of European Universities to interest them in Nationality Rooms, 1925; Building Committee correspondence; Minutes of the City Planning Commission of Pittsburgh, August 25, 1926; Building Committee's recommendations; Special meetings of the Board; Request for rezoning in order to build Cathedral of Learning; Correspondence about securing a contractor; Tried to secure motion pictures of the construction of Cathedral of Learning from Motion Picture Producing Co., Pittsburgh, PA – but too expensive?; Proposal to organize an Evening Division, February 1926
- Tuesday Musical Club (Box 11, Folder 94)
  Form for agreement between the Club and the University, 1931; Planning and cost estimates for the Stephen Foster Memorial; Photograph of the proposed drawing; Statement of assets; Contract with Ketchum, Inc. to manage fund collection for Stephen Foster Memorial Hall; Short tale about Stephen Foster, by Dr. Bowman
- Correspondence: Uhrich - U.S. Army (Box 11, Folder 95)
  U.S. Steel concerning steel requirements for the cyclotron, 1941; U.S. Army seeking universities to participate in various activities,1941-47
- Civil Affairs Training Specialist Program (Box 11, Folder 96)
  Civil Affairs Training School pamphlets, Class 1 and 2; 1943-44; (includes biographies of faculty and students); Civil Affairs Training Specialist Program. Division of Area and Language study; Lists of people who can teach specialties, and a biography of each, 1943; Letters: Hyneman, F.H. Smith letter and other information on "Communist speaker" Gailmor
- Army Specialized Training Program (Box 11, Folder 97-98)
  Pamphlets: "ASTP Foreign Area and Language Studies "A" Group" (Roster) from Army; "Essential Facts About the Army Specialized Training Program (Roster of trainees); AST Program Manual Memos from Army Service Forces; ARMY Specialized Training Bulletin no 2-4. Biennial Reports and Comments and criticisms (Engineering, Medicine, Language studies; articles on Pitt mobilization for war
  Separated Material
  Folder 98 has be relocated to Box 12
- Air Crew Training Program (Box 12, Folder 99)
  Supplemental Agreement to Contract No. W 30-053 ac-63; Supplement to Manual M-102: Memorandum on financing Army Trainee program; Lists of Air Corps members, by squadron, 1943; Letters and memos concerning many phases of this activity; clippings; text of Hanley speech
- University of Pittsburgh Press (Box 12, Folder 100)
  Memos on income and expenses, 1936-39; Gift of $30,000 from Mellon Educational and Charitable Trust; Catalog: Americana, 1941; and 1942; Sales and stock report, December 31, 1941; Memos and letters; 1965-66 catalogs added
- Veterans Affairs and Veterans Administration (Box 12, Folder 101)
  1944 material; courses at University; Vocational rehabilitation training; Contracts with Veterans Administration
- Correspondence: Wallace bequest - War Manpower Commission (Box 12, Folder 102)
  Correspondence concerning the bequest of Daniel H. Wallace – took 20 years to settle; Memorial endowment for George Leonard Walter, Jr., 1923?; Washington & Jefferson gave honorary degree of Doctor of Laws to Chancellor Bowman on June 24, 1944; War Manpower Commission, 1944 – concerning students for military, courses; survey of colleges and universities for suitability
- John Weber, correspondence and reports (Box 12, Folder 103-103a)
  1945/46 chart of number of professors, degrees, men or women, etc; Steam line for boiler plant with Mellon Institute; Memos of notes given to Miss Wolfel for Executive Committee; Data on School of Medicine, 1936; Proposal for student activities building, 1936; Estimate of cost if to purchase Webster Hall for dormitory, 1931; Commons Room information (statistics as to stone, bricks, etc.; Building in progress, 1936; Commons Room, estimated cost for completion; Elevator cost contract; Work planned for Cathedral, February – May 1934; Labor furnished by Civil Works Administration, 1934; Budget policy, 1933/34; Employment of workers from Allegheny County Emergency Association 1931; Work done on the Darlington Library; Memos about Funds; Mr. John Weber's letters to Chancellor Bowman concerning the building of Cathedral of Learning and his talks with Mr. Klauder the architect; Migration of foreign nationalities to Pittsburgh, 1890-1920, tables; (103A contains material on Cathedral of Learning construction)
  File 103a has been relocated to Box 13
- Westinghouse Electric and Air Brake - Young (Box 13, Folder 104)
  Letter to Mr. A.W. Roberston, expressing thanks for the Westinghouse Company's gift for the electrical equipment for the cyclotron, 1942; This gift inspired other contributions; Gift by Westinghouse Air-Brake to Cathedral in 1934; Emil Winter doantion to Cathedral of Learning; Plans for faculty housing; Letters concerning state of the Alumni Association; Letters from Samuel Yellin (metalworker); Letters concerning planning of the Children's Hospital (Dr. Huggins and Mr. Franklin); Letters: Willits, Williams, Winters estate,
- Financial Campaign, 1930 (Box 13, Folder 105)
  Conducted by J. Steele Gow during Dr. Bowman's absence in Europe because of illness; Fund raising to finish the building of the Cathedral of Learning; Material dated April – June 1930 with some items from 1925 and 1927; Tables, lists, letters and memos
- Financial Campaign, 1932-1934 (Box 13, Folder 106)
  Conducted by Ketchum, Inc. Pamphlet: "Finish the Cathedral"; Chancellor Bowman's letters from Ketchum, including some from and 1934; Letters and memos about campaign
- Financial Campaign, 1934 (Box 13, Folder 107)
  Notes on the organization of the campaign efforts
- Financial Campaign, 1934 (Box 13, Folder 108)
  Primary Gifts Committee; A.E. Braun; Letters and memos on planning and securing workers
- Financial Campaign, 1934 (Box 13, Folder 109)
  Women's Committee
- Financial Campaign, 1934 (Box 13, Folder 110)
  Fundraising dinners, Primary Gifts, Ketchum; 1934
- Financial Campaign, 1934 (Box 14, Folder 111)
  Complete the Cathedral Committee; Sample letters; Ketchum correspondence; List of "One hundred great names" with short biographies
- Financial Campaign, 1934 (Box 14, Folder 112)
  Memos and general correspondence; Letters of appreciation for work done on campaign
- Financial Campaign, 1934 (Box 14, Folder 113)
  Progress reports no. 1-9 (1934 weekly) from Ketchum; Programs for Annual Parents Reception, 1949, 1950, 1952, 1954 plus sample invitation
- Financial Campaign, 1934 (Box 14, Folder 114)
  General publicity for Cathedral, Cathedral information sheet 1934, Application for Civil Works Project funds; R. E. Watson donation letters; Historical paper by Holland; 1935 "Complete the Cathedral" poster
- Financial Campaign, 1934 (Box 14, Folder 115)
  Press releases and publicity for 1934 campaign to finish the cathedral; Newspaper clippings; List of 100 historic Pittsburghers; Activities during campaign; Leechburg, Once 'Friendship', got start in old Pennsylvania Canal days
- Financial Campaign, 1934 (Box 14, Folder 116)
  Samples of forms, letters, memos used in campaign
- Financial Campaign, 1934 (Box 14, Folder 117)
  Lists of subscribers and efforst to re-start fundraising; sample letters
- Financial Campaign, 1934 (Box 14, Folder 118)
  Solicitation reports for "Complete the Cathedral" campaign
- Financial Campaign, 1934 (Box 14, Folder 119)
  Steering Committee Minutes of meetings from March 1934
- Financial Campaign, 1934 (Box 14, Folder 120)
  Campaign Subscriptions – General correspondence and sample of brochure
- Financial Campaign, 1934 (Box 15, Folder 121)
  Primary gifts Assignment sheets
- Financial Campaign, 1934 (Box 15, Folder 122)
  Citizens committee Assignment sheets
- Financial Campaign, 1934 (Box 15, Folder 123)
  Corporations committee Assignment sheets
- Financial Campaign, 1934 (Box 15, Folder 124)
  Women's committee Assignment sheets
- Financial Campaign, 1934 (Box 15, Folder 125)
  Faculty committee Assignment sheets
- Financial Campaign, 1925 (Box 16, Folder 126)
  Campaign by Ketchum Co.; Memos; Letters (some Chancellor Bowman's); Lists of meetings; Speeches; List of dinner guests; sample invitations; Scholarships to Stanko sisters: Material for Judge Gary including program and menu; Technology plan; 2 Cathedral of Learning Stamps
- Financial Campaign, 1925 (Box 16, Folder 127)
  Letters and memos concerning pledges and plans 1925-1934; Some funds from Nationality Groups for Rooms; Letters about the Darlington Library collection from John Oliver (History) and J. Howard Dice (Library)
- Cathedral of Learning publicity (Box 16, Folder 128)
  Articles written by Chancellor Bowman for release to Newspaper; "A cathedral of the spirit of achievement:' "The educational meaning of the "Cathedral"; Clipping from New York Times Magazine, June 17, 1928 – "A tower of inspiration to a busy city;" Letters from abroad asking about the Cathedral
- Financial Campaign, 1925 (Box 16, Folder 129)
  Newspaper clippings and comments; Varied assortment of articles and letters and opinions some from overseas; Pittsburgh Press article on Steelworkers who built Cathedral - Nov. 3, 1929.
- Financial Campaign, 1925-1930 (Box 16, Folder 130)
  Fundraising plans and memos soliciting foreign clubs and groups; Naionality Rooms dinner
- Day and Klauder, Architects, 1925 (Box 16, Folder 131)
  Biography of Mr. Klauder; Correspondence between Chancellor Bowman and Mr. Klauder concerning plans for the Cathedral of Learning; Agreement for design; List of changes, inscriptions, etc.; Letters of Tenney & Ohmes, consulting engineers and Mr. Balcom (1924)
- Stone and Weber, Engineers, 1924-1929 (Box 16, Folder 132)
  Correspondence with Chancellor Bowman; An article: "The architect"; Copies of Contract for the construction of a University building…between University of Pittsburgh and Stone & Webster, Inc. Dated December 4, 1924
- Liberal Club, 1929 (Box 17, Folder 133)
  Pittsburgh ACLU members, including some University staff; Includes correspondence re expulsion of Frederick Waltman, graduate assistant and students Albertson and McDowell for activities in Liberal Club; Bill of complaint from McDowell and Albertson. Letters in support and against the Pitt Liberal Club; Letters reference Coal and Iron Police and Mooney-Billings
- Liberal Club, 1929 (Box 17, Folder 134)
  Clippings from newspapers and journals about the dismissal of the Liberal Club and the expulsion of the students and faculty. Telegrams from other Universities.
- Liberal Club, 1934-1935 (Box 17, Folder 135)
  Correspondence: dismissal of Ralph E. Turner, Legislative investigation 1935 and report, AAUP Investigation, Rep. Ellenbogen and Gov. Pinchot letters, statement by A.W. Mellon; Some photocopies re investigation; partial list of speakers addressing the student body 1929-1935; Notes from an address by Dr. Turner at the Heinz House in 1930. Letter from Holt (Rollins College) regarding their dismissal from AAUP, Rollins College Bulletin: Rollins College vs AAUP
- Liberal Club controversy, 1934-1936 (Box 17, Folder 135a, 135b, 135c)
  Extensive reporting on the Liberal Club, dismissal and resignations of faculty and student reactions.
- Ralph Turner and the Liberal Club controversy, 1934-1935 (Box 17, Folder 136-136a)
  Letters from individuals and organizations expressing opinions on the dismissal of Ralph Turner. Clippings from newspapers on the controversy.
- Ralph E. Turner controversy (Box 18, Folder 137)